Baron Gracias

barongracias@gmail.com | +44 7561 313823 | linkedin.com/in/baron-gracias

SUMMARY

Data scientist with over **3-years** of experience in payments. Worked with terabyte-scale databases and delivered £3m/year analytics. An academic background in Physics, possessing proven skills in **Python**, **SQL**, and data story-telling. Strong ability to present insights and tailor communication to wide audiences for data-driven decision-making.

SKILLS

Programming: Python (NumPy, Pandas, Dask, scikit-learn), SQL (T-SQL, PL/SQL, SQLite), command line.

Data Science & Software: Machine learning, MLOps, Git and version control, exploratory analysis, data visualisation.

Mathematics: Statistics, probability theory, linear algebra, discrete maths, calculus, numerical methods.

EXPERIENCE

Mastercard 2022 - Present

Data Scientist

- UK payments: managed Teradata and Oracle TB-scale data warehouse, leveraging big data processing skills.
- Office for National Statistics (ONS): Led and owned a multi-million pound ML service which classifies 15m accounts per month as business or personal with over 90% accuracy.
- ONS: delivered exploratory analysis on pandemic payment trends, revealing over 20 indicators for economic shock.
- Open Banking: built a "Spotify Wrapped" inspired expenditure insights model that achieved 90% user engagement.
- Git implementation: led the creation of a centralised Git repository, standardising code management practices and mitigated code conflicts, this improved team efficiency and multiplied release cycles by 1.5x.

Data Engineer 2020 - 2021

- Placement year, managed GB-scale SSMS data warehouse, Alteryx ETL pipelines and Postman API frameworks.
- Created BI dashboards, reporting KPIs and visualising data for senior leadership, with 3x usage rate improvements.
- Built a prescriptive resource management tool, with an accuracy of 99.6%, allowing PMs to more precisely book timesheets; reducing under/over-utilisation. Aligned £3m/year in project financials and boosted capacity by 200%.

PROJECTS

Fraud EDA: Explored the emergence of economic crime to improve fraud detection, creating a data quality dashboard that increased performance on models by up to **10%**. Utilised Dask and multiprocessing to parse multi-**GB** dataframe.

Mastercard Sports Lead: Founded several sports teams by successfully pitching to C-suite and EVPs for funding to enter corporate charity events and donating over £20k to CRUK from fundraising and winning inter/national tournaments.

Data conferences: Representative at ConfX Analytics Summit Amsterdam, HPE Data Science LDN, and Big Data LDN.

EDUCATION

University of Bath 2018 - 2022

BSc Physics

- **Awarded high first-class**. Fine-tuned analytical and abstract problem-solving skills for loosely defined problems. Skilled in designing experiments, mathematical modelling, communicating and presenting complex ideas.
- **R&D Scientist, Malvern Panalytical**: Developed a Python image processing algorithm for HDR laser intensity measurements, yielding 5 orders of magnitude improvement against industry standards.

Certifications 2024

- Data Science Specialization, IBM, 10-part course exploring methodologies and applications with Python, SQL, R.
- Machine Learning Specialization, DL.AI, covering core ML concepts in un/supervised and reinforcement learning.
- Machine Learning in Production, DL.AI, exploring best practises in ML deployment, monitoring and optimisation.